<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Pogamut installation</title>

  <section>
    <title>Installation steps</title>

    <para></para>

    <section>
      <title>JDK and Netbeans</title>

      <para>Before you install Pogamut you have to have installed JDK 1.6+ and
      Netbeans 7.1.1 if you want to use the Pogamut Netbeans plugin which
      brings many handy features.</para>

      <para>There are two possibilities:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>you have neither JDK nor Netbeans, then it is easiest to
          download latest <link
          xlink:href="http://java.sun.com/javase/downloads/widget/jdk_netbeans.jsp">Netbeans
          and JDK cobundle</link>.</para>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="media/install/NbJavaBundleInstall.png"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>you already have JDK 1.6+ but you don't have Netbeans, then
          follow this <link
          xlink:href="http://netbeans.org/downloads/index.html">link for
          download</link>. "Java SE" version will be sufficient.</para>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="media/install/NBDownload.png"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Unreal</title>

      <para>Current Pogamut can communicate with both Unreal Tournament 2004
      (UT2004), Unreal Engine 2 Runtime (UE2) and Unreal Development Kit (UDK).</para>

      <para>UT2004 is a commercial game and you have to buy it if you want to
      connect to this environment.</para>

      <para>UE2 is free for noncommercial use, you can <link
      xlink:href="http://apacudn.epicgames.com/Two/UnrealEngine2Runtime22262002.html">download
      it here</link>. But preferably, install it with <link xlink:href="http://diana.ms.mff.cuni.cz/main/tiki-index.php?page=Download">Pogamut Emohawk Installer</link>.</para>
      
      <para>UDK is a free version of Unreal Engine 3. We distribute free UDK
      version installer with built-in GameBots in Pogamut installer.
      </para>

    </section>
	
	<section>
    <title>Pogamut installation</title>
    
    <para>To install Pogamut download Pogamut from the <link
    xlink:href="http://diana.ms.mff.cuni.cz/main/tiki-index.php?page=Download">download
    page</link>. Installer is Java .jar file, you will be probably able to
    run it directly from your file manager, if not then type <command>java
    -jar Pogamut-3-installer.jar</command> in your command line. </para>	
    <para>Installer will guide you through the rest of installation
    process. Note that we offer several installers depending on which environment you want to use for your bots. Currently you can decide between
	UT2004 (thoroughly debugged, used for several years on our courses, provides first person shooter scenario), UnrealEngine2RuntimeDemo aka PogamutEmohawk (debugged, provides non-violent scenario),
	DEFCON (working proof of concept, provides realtime strategy game environment) and UDK (working proof of concept, provides somehow limited first person shooter
	scenario in good graphics and its free to use). Bots developed for different environments are usually not compatible!</para>	
	
    <para>Moreover, as Pogamut 3 has been fully mavenized (read more about Maven at <link
      xlink:href="http://maven.apache.org/">Maven homepage</link>), you can now follow <link
          xlink:href="http://pogamut.cuni.cz/pogamut_files/doc/Setup-Pogamut3-with-Maven.pdf">Pogamut 3 with Maven Quickstart Tutorial</link> with all necessary steps to setup latest Pogamut version
          and start developing Pogamut bots (but WITHOUT Pogamut NetBeans plugin). However, we recommend to set up Pogamut with Pogamut installer as it is much easier. 
		  To see a list of all Pogamut Maven archetypes you may use to start developing your bot visit our <link
          xlink:href="http://diana.ms.mff.cuni.cz:8081/artifactory/libs-release-local/archetype-catalog.xml"> Pogamut Maven archetypes catalog</link>. We recommend to use latest archetypes versions that are AT THE BOTTOM of the file!.</para>
  </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
