<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE commandobject SYSTEM "../GBMessages.dtd">

<commandobject command="ADDRAY" extends="CommandMessage" name="AddRay" type="Configure">
   <gbpackage name="GameBots2004"/>
   <gbpackage name="GBScenario"/>
   <gbpackage name="GameBotsAnim"/>
   <gbpackage name="GameBotsUE2"/>
   <gbpackage name="GBEmohawk"/>
   <group name="Bot"/>
   <documentation>
		Add custom ray for automatic ray tracing. If you send Id =
		Default, all rays will be erased and default set of rays will be
		loaded (straight ahead (1,0,0) with 250 length, 45 degrees left
		(1,–1,0) with 200 length, 45 degrees right (1,1,0) with 200
		length). This set of rays is also loaded by default. If you want
		to change existing ray, just support its Id in ADDRAY command
		along with new parameters. Direction of the rays work as
		follows. Bot is looking to x axis, that means if I want ray
		straight ahead I specify some vector on positive x axis (vectors
		in unreal are specified by (x,y,z) so it would look like this
		(1,0,0) or this (123,0,0) – numbers doesn't matter, its about
		direction - vectors will be normalized). If I want ray behind it
		would be (–1,0,0). 90 degrees right (0,1,0) etc.
	</documentation>
   <!-- List of all properties of this command. !--><property name="Id" type="String">
      <documentation>
			User set Id of the ray, so the ray can be identified.
		</documentation>
   </property>
   <property name="Direction" type="Vector3d">
      <documentation>
			Vector direction of the ray (it will be relative - added to
			the vector, where the bot is looking, also takes into
			account angle of the floor the bot is standing on).
		</documentation>
   </property>
   <property name="Length" type="int">
      <documentation>
			Specifies the length of the ray (in UT units).
		</documentation>
   </property>
   <property name="FastTrace" type="boolean">
      <documentation>
			True if we want to use FastTrace function instead of Trace
			function (a bit faster but less information provided - just
			information if we hit something or not).
		</documentation>
   </property>
   <property name="FloorCorrection" type="boolean">
      <documentation>
      If we should correct ray directions accoring floor normal. Note: Has issue - we can't set set rays up or down when correction is active.
		</documentation>
   </property>
   <property name="TraceActors" type="boolean">
      <documentation>
			If we want to trace also actors – bots, monsters, players,
			items. False if we want to trace just level geometry.
		</documentation>
   </property>
   <!-- Extra information used by different modules of the Pogamut platform. !--><extra>
      <code/>
   </extra>
</commandobject>