<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE commandobject SYSTEM "../GBMessages.dtd">

<commandobject command="INIT" extends="CommandMessage" name="Initialize" type="Configure">
   <gbpackage name="GameBots2004"/>
   <gbpackage name="GBScenario"/>
   <gbpackage name="GameBotsAnim"/>
   <gbpackage name="GameBotsUE2"/>
   <gbpackage name="GBEmohawk"/>
   <group name="Bot"/>
   <documentation>
		Message you'll send at the beginning of the communication to
		create a bot in the game. You must send this message before you
		can have a character to play in the game.
	</documentation>
   <!-- List of all properties of this command. !--><property name="Name" type="String">
      <documentation>Desired name.</documentation>
   </property>
   <property name="Team" type="int">
      <documentation>
			Preferred team. If illegal or no team provided, one will be
			provided for you. Normally a team game has team 0 and team
			1. In BotDeathMatch, team is meaningless.
		</documentation>
   </property>
   <property name="ManualSpawn" type="boolean">
      <documentation>
			Sets if the bot wil have tol be respawned after death
			manually by RESPAWN command. If false, the bot will respawn
			automatically.
		</documentation>
   </property>
   <property name="AutoTrace" type="boolean">
      <documentation>
			Enables/disables auto ray tracing feature.
		</documentation>
   </property>
   <property name="Location" type="Location">
      <documentation>
			Specify start location, if unspecified, then random.
		</documentation>
   </property>
   <property name="Rotation" type="Rotation">
      <documentation>
			Specify start rotation, if unspecified, then random.
		</documentation>
   </property>
   <property name="Skin" type="String">
      <documentation>
			Sets the bot current skin (e.g. "HumanMaleA.MercMaleA").
			Find all packages and skins through unrealEd (Actor browser,
			search in UT2004/Animations folder). Supported bot skins are
			Aliens (Aliens.), Bots (Bot.), human males (HumanMaleA.),
			human females (HumanFemaleA. ), juggernauts (Jugg.). Skaarj
			skins are not supported at the time being.
		</documentation>
   </property>
   <property name="DesiredSkill" type="int">
      <documentation>
			Can range from 0 to 7. This sets the bot accuracy. 1 lowest,
			7 highest. Shouldn't have any other effect.
		</documentation>
   </property>
   <property name="ShouldLeadTarget" type="boolean">
      <documentation>
			When firing slow projectiles (missiles...), if the engine
			will try to count the impact point for the bot or not (when
			shooting at moving targets).
		</documentation>
   </property>
   <property name="AutoPickupOff" type="boolean">
      <documentation>
			It enables/disables automatic pickup of the bot. If true the items can be picked up through PICK command.
		</documentation>
   </property>
   <property name="NewSelfBatchProtocol" type="boolean">
      <documentation>
			If set to true new synchronous batch procotol will be used. Sync. batches will be sent
			more regularly containing SELF message only (based on SelfUpdateTime value). Visibility
			information will be still sent in synchronous batches, but not always, but each VisionTime.
			VisionTime now needs to be multiple of SelfUpdateTime and will be set to nearest multiple if 
			set improperly. BEG and END message will contain new attribute VisUpdate telling if visibility
			update is sent in this batch or not.
		</documentation>
   </property>   
   <property name="Jmx" type="String">
      <documentation>
			Sets the jmx adress we can use to debug the bot from Java (if we are using Pogamut).
		</documentation>
   </property>
   <property name="ClassName" type="String">
      <documentation>
			Sets the Unreal Tournament class of the bot that should be used. By default leave it blank. In UnrealRuntime2 it may be used to spawn bots of different class,
			see CharacterType class in project PogamutEmohawk project.
		</documentation>
   </property>
   <!-- Extra information used by different modules of the Pogamut platform. !--><extra>
      <code/>
   </extra>
</commandobject>